how is the free test total test Ratio
calculated I understand it should be
about 3% unit conversion
required yeah so it's it's difficult uh
to answer questions like this because
there's different units used all over
the world I mean in Europe there's
different units used from country to
Country it's when you're Consulting
International clients it's an absolute
nightmare um sometimes they even print
the units wrong so if you're in Europe
and you're looking at your blood test
and it doesn't look right sometimes they
actually print the wrong units happens
more often than thing um so it's not so
much how is The Ratio calculated or what
should the ratio be free testosterone is
calculated based on your shbg and your
albumin albumin tends to stay more
constant albumin is typically measured
as part of a liver panel so albumin
doesn't vary that much unless you've got
like liver disease but shbg varies a
huge amount personto person so depending
on where your shbg sits will depend on
your ratio of total to free testost
and having a very high or a very low
shbg can be pathological I I have a very
simple way of stating this if shbg has
got one number or three numbers you
might have a problem if it's between 10
and 99 it's probably fine now if you're
a younger guy and you've got an shbg of
95 then of course then that could be
suggesting something too but as a
general rule of thumb there's a very
broad goal post that shbg sits within
based on genetics the two things
although the handful of things sorry
that I see influence shbg either up or
down that people should be aware of one
is that hypothyroidism and insulin
resistance will often lower shbg and
that's something that should be assessed
as part of a comprehensive review anyway
but that can be a red flag that those
things need to be looked at so maybe if
someone's got you know a borderline
thyroid panel and they've got an shbg
that's very low that would warrant you
know looking into running Hashim Motors
antibodies but I think people should
just test them anyway
and one thing that increases shbg a lot
which a lot of people don't look at is
SSRI anti-depressants five Alpha
reductase Inhibitors vegetarian and
vegan diets so vegetarian and vegan
diets will increase shbg without
increasing total testosterone which
leads to a lower free testosterone ratio
so there are also being in you know
ketosis long term or being in you know
deep caloric restriction long term will
raise it too as part of the body's
survival adaptation so when it comes to
s BG it's important to recognize that
genetics are a big factor there can be
pathologies leading it to be high or low
but what's going to determine an
individuals free to Total testosterone
ratio is primarily going to be based on
their shbg
[Music]